A Finding Aid to the William Page and Page Family Papers, 1815-1947, bulk 1843-1892, in the Archives of American Art AAA.pagewill
Archives of American Art
William Page and Page Family papers
bulk 1843-1892
1815-1947
AAA.pagewill
Archives of American Art
8.5 Linear feet
The papers of the portraitist and art theorist William Page and the Page family measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1815 to 1947, bulk 1843-1892. In addition to the papers of William Page, the papers include documents related to Page's wife's career as a writer and records documenting their personal lives and the lives of their family members. Types of documents found include personal documents and artifacts, correspondence, essays, lectures, diaries, poems, notes and notebooks, financial records, legal records, published works, clippings, catalogs, photographs, and artwork.
Page, William
Provenance
A portion of the collection was donated to the Archives of American Art by Mrs. Lesslie S. (Pauline Page) Howell, William Page's grandaughter, in 1963. William S. Page, Pauline Page Howell's nephew, donated additional papers in 1964 and 1973. Mrs. Howell's son, William Page Howell, donated material in 1980.
Letters of Charles F. Briggs to James Russell Lowell (Series 2.2) were a part of Pauline Page Howell's 1963 donation to the Archives of American Art. They had been given to Mrs. Howell by Charlotte Briggs, daughter of Charles F. Briggs, because of her father's lifelong friendship with William Page. Letters from Lowell to Briggs are in the James Russell Lowell papers in Houghton Library at Harvard University.
Separated Material
Pauline Page Howell and William S. Page loaned a group of letters to the Archives in 1964 which were microfilmed on reel 1091 and then returned to the donors. These include letters from Elizabeth Barrett and Robert Browning, Lydia Maria Child, Charlotte Cushman, James Russell Lowell, Charles A. Dana, and others. This material is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of William Page in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2007, and total 15514 images.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
The painter William Page was born in 1811 in Albany, NY. He attended public schools in New York City, and after working briefly in the law firm of Frederick de Peyster, was placed in the studio of the painter/engraver James Herring in 1825, where he received his first formal art training. He took classes at the National Academy of Design the year it was formed, in 1826, under Samuel F.B. Morse, and in 1827 he was awarded one of the National Academy's first annual student prizes.
Page joined the Presbyterian church and attended Phillips Academy and Amherst with the intention of becoming a minister, but his artistic ability won out, and by 1830 he was painting commissioned portraits in Albany, Rochester, and New York. He married Lavinia Twibill in 1833, and they had three daughters between 1834 and 1839. He joined the American Academy and served on its board of directors in 1835. He exhibited at the American Academy, the National Academy of Design, the Boston Athenaeum, and other venues throughout the 1830s. Favorable reviews brought steady portrait commissions, including John Quincy Adams and the New York governor William L. Marcy. He was made a full member of the National Academy in 1837.
In the 1840s, Page's reputation and maturity as a painter grew. His first wife left him around 1840, and in 1843 he married Sarah Dougherty. The couple moved to Albany, Boston, and back to New York seeking portrait commissions and patronage. He became friends with the poet James Russell Lowell and the writer and publisher Charles Frederick Briggs, two writers and editors who helped to promote his artwork in Boston and New York and published his theoretical writings. In 1844, Lowell dedicated his first published book of poetry to Page, and the following year, Briggs published a series of articles by Page in the Broadway Journal, entitled "The Art of the Use of Color in Imitation in Painting." The series described Page's arduous experiments with color and glazes, and his ideas about correspondences between spirituality and the natural world as expressed in art.
In 1850, Page traveled to Florence, Italy, where he painted several copies of the works of Titian in the galleries of the Uffizi and Pitti palaces, studying his use of color and further developing his own experimental techniques. He became friends with the sculptor Hiram Powers, who introduced him to the writings of Emmanuel Swedenborg, a Christian metaphysician whose ideas fueled Page's interest in the spiritual aspects of art. In 1852, Page moved to Rome, a city with an international artists' community and a strong market for art. Page found a loyal following in Rome's large circle of American ex-patriates, including the sculptors Thomas Crawford and Harriet Hosmer, the actress Charlotte Cushman, and the poets Robert and Elizabeth Barrett Browning, all of whom sat for portraits by Page.
In 1854, Page's second wife left him amidst public scandal, and he sank deep in debt to his bankers at Packenham and Hooker, an English firm that by 1856 had a lien on all the paintings in his studio. That same year Page met Sophia Stevens Hitchcock, an American widow traveling in Rome with Bertha Olmsted, Frederick Law Olmsted's sister. Hitchcock was from Barnet, Vermont and came to Europe after her first husband died in 1852 after only a year of marriage. She traveled to England and Paris, where she wrote regular columns on local customs and events for the New York Tribune that were published under the by-line "An American Woman in Paris." She and Page met in Rome in 1856, and in October 1857, after Page traveled back the United States to obtain a divorce from Sarah Dougherty, he and Sophia married.
The couple stayed in Rome until 1860. His wife's three brothers, all businessmen, helped to promote his artwork in Europe and America. Page's paintings of this period include several Venus subjects, one of which was championed by his most loyal patrons, who raised $3000 by subscription to buy the painting for the Boston Athenaeum. A later Venus painting was rejected from the Paris salon for indecency, a controversy that was later leveraged for publicity in a touring exhibition in the United States.
The Pages returned to the United States in 1860 and settled in Tottenville, New York. They had six children between 1858 and 1870. Page had a studio at Eagleswood, NJ, and later in the Studio Building on 10th Street in Manhattan, where he held a large exhibition in 1867. In the 1860s, he painted a self-portrait and a companion portrait of Sophia set in Rome, as well as a series of civil war heroes including Robert Gould Shaw, Winfield Scott, and David Farragut. Photographs played a consistent part in Page's technique of portraiture, and he is known to have worked with the photographer Matthew Brady, who attended art classes early on with Page, as well as the photographers Sarony and Charles Williamson, who taught classes on drawing from enlarged photo-transparencies. Brady photographs taken for Page include David Farragut and Reuben Fenton.
Page lectured frequently on Titian and Venetian art, a subject in which he was considered an expert, and on painting technique and his philosophical ideas about nature, art, and spirituality. In 1871, Page was elected the president of the National Academy of Design, a post he held until 1873, but his poor health following a collapse in 1872 limited his accomplishments in office. Despite these limitations, he continued to paint, including portraits of General Grant, an idealized portrait of the president based on early photographs and Charles Sumner. He also became interested in portraiture of William Shakespeare around this time, and his studies resulted in a book, Shakespeare's Portraits, a bust based on existing portraiture, and a full-length portrait entitled "Shakespeare Reading," based on Page's measurements of a supposed death mask in Darmstadt, Germany, which he went to inspect against the advice of his doctor in 1874.
In 1877, another collapse left Page incapacitated for the remainder of his life. Sophia Page tried editing and publishing his writings and lectures, but with little success. Page died in 1885. A life marked by personal scandal ended the same, when two of his daughters from his first marriage contested his will, tying up his estate in a lengthy and public probate trial. Their suit was dismissed in 1889, and Sophia Page died in 1892.
This biography relies heavily on Joshua Taylor's William Page: The American Titian (1957).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the painter William Page and the Page family measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1815 to 1947, with the bulk of papers dating from 1843 to 1892. Papers contain records related to the life and career of William Page, president of the National Academy of Design from 1871 to 1873 and prominent portraitist and art theorist of his day. Also found are records related to his wife's career as a writer and records documenting their personal lives and the lives of their family members. Types of documents found include personal documents and artifacts, correspondence, essays, lectures, diaries, poems, notes and notebooks, financial records, legal records, published works, clippings, catalogs, photographs, and artwork.
Correspondence includes the personal and professional correspondence of William and Sophia Page, and their parents, siblings, and children. Significant correspondents include Thomas Hicks, Enoch Wood Perry, William Stark, Theodore Tilton, Lemuel Wilmarth, Wendell Phillips, William Walker Scranton, Francis G. Shaw; James Russell Lowell, Charles Frederick Briggs, George W. Curtis, Charlotte Cushman, Thomas K. Beecher, Mary Olmsted, and Bertha Olmsted.
Writings include the essays and lectures of William Page, as written by him and revised by Sophia Page in the late 1870s, as well as Sophia's writings as a columnist in Europe in the 1850s. Notes, notebooks, diaries, and poems are also found. Personal Business Records include business records related to the sale and exhibition of artwork as well as financial and legal documents. A small number of memoranda and documents related to Page's work at the National Academy of Design are also found. Printed Materials include exhibition catalogs, published works by William and Sophia Page, and clippings and articles about Page.
Photographs consist mainly of portraits, most of them mounted cabinet photographs or cartes-des-visites, some of which appear to have been used as studies for Page's painted portraits. Among those pictured are William Page, James Russell Lowell, Henry Ward Beecher, Reuben Fenton, Wendell Phillips, Charles Sumner, William R. O'Donovan, and William Lloyd Garrison. Many of the photographic portraits are unidentified. Artwork includes sketches, drawings, prints, and a small number of notes made by Page in the course of painting portraits.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Materials and Artifacts, 1847-1917 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1815-1942 (Boxes 1-4, 9-10; 3.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1839-1888, 1949 (Boxes 4-5, OV 10; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1848-1932 (Boxes 5 and 9; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials, 1845-1938 (Boxes 5-7, 9, OV 11; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1845-1947 (Boxes 7-9, OV 12, MGP 5-6; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1856-1874 (Box 8, OV 13-16, rolled documents 17-19; 0.6 linear feet and 3 rolled documents)
Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887; Beecher, Thomas Kinnicut, 1824-1900; Briggs, Charles F. (Charles Frederick), 1804-1877; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892; Cushman, Charlotte, 1816-1876; Fenton, Rueben; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879; Hicks, Thomas, 1823-1890; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891; National Academy of Design (U.S.).; O'Donovan, William Rudolph, 1844-1920; Olmstead, Bertha; Olmstead, Mary; Page, Sophia Stevens, 1827-1892; Page, William, 1811-1885; Perry, E. W. (Enoch Wood), 1831-1915; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884; Scranton, William Walker; Shaw, Francis George, 1809-1882; Stark, William, 1825-1873; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874; Tilton, Theodore, 1835-1907; Wilmarth, Lemuel Everett, 1835-1918; Diaries; Drawings; Photographs; Poems; Portrait painters--New York (State)--New York; Portrait painting--19th century--New York (State)--New York; Sketches; Works of art
- Biographical Materials and Artifacts, 1847-1917, undated; Series 1; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Personal artifacts and documents in this series relate to William Page, his family, and his in-laws, the Stevens family.
  Narratives include an obituary of Page written by the engraver W.J. Linton and a copy of an 1883 biographical article about Page. Personal documents of the Pages include two handwritten statements, one regarding his marriage to Sophia Page, and the other regarding his citizenship.
  Personal documents of the Page children include school-related documents and traveling expenses. Personal documents of the Stevens family include Henry Stevens' passport, lists of personal items, and death notices. Medical items include the autopsy of Robert Kemble, a prescription, and phrenological charts.
  Annotated postcards and maps identify the birthplace of Sophia Page, the Page family residence, and burial sites. Artifacts include an autographed calling card signed by Page, Launt Thompson, Charles H. Miller, and others, possibly all be artists from the 10th Street Studio Building in New York City; locks of hair; and a hand-carved wooden pen.
  - Narratives about William Page, 1885, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Documents of William and Sophia Page, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Documents of Page Children, 1878-1881, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Documents of Stevens Family, 1847-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical Documents, 1853, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Birthplace, Home, and Burial Sites, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Autographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Locks of Hair, 1867-1884, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hand-carved Fountain Pen, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1815-1942, undated; Series 2; (Boxes 1-4, 9-10; 3.2 linear feet)
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence of William and Sophia Page and their children, as well as family correspondence of the Hitchcock and Stevens families. Also found are letters written by the publisher Charles Frederick Briggs to the poet James Russell Lowell and to William Page in the 1840s.
  Arrangement note
  The Correspondence series is arranged into 3 subseries:
  2.1: General Correspondence, 1815-1942, undated
  2.2: Charles Frederick Briggs Correspondence, 1843-1846, undated
  2.3: Sophia Stevens and Stephen Hitchcock Correspondence, 1847-1852
  - General Correspondence, 1815-1942, undated; 2.1
    Letters in this series include the personal and professional correspondence of William Page, his wife, Sophia Candace Stevens Page, and their families, as well as correspondence of Sophia Page's first husband Stephen Hitchcock and his family.
    William Page's correspondence is found from 1833 to 1885 only, with the bulk of his correspondence dating from 1852 to 1877. Drafts of outgoing letters written by William and Sophia Page are found throughout the series. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated correspondence filed alphabetically by author at the end of the series. Correspondence of Page's children, which is voluminous from the early 1880s onward, and other family correspondence of the Page, Stevens, and Hitchcock families has not been indexed.
    The earliest correspondence is that of Page's relatives of the Mathies, Dunnel, and Baldwin families of New York State. From 1840 through 1852, much of the correspondence is that of the Hitchcock family. See Series 2.3 for correspondence between Sophia and Steven Hitchcock. Love letters between William Page and Sophia (then Hitchcock) are prevalent in 1857, the year they were married. Family correspondence among Sophia Page, her parents, and her brothers Henry, B. Frank, and Simon Stevens is prevalent from the 1850s through the 1880s. By 1884, much of the correspondence is that of the Page children, including their personal, business, and family correspondence. A long, amorous correspondence from Charlotte "Sharly" Briggs to Candace "Dacie" Page, which documents an apparently intimate relationship between the two women, is found from the late 1880s onward, with many undated letters.
    William Page's significant correspondents include artists such as Thomas Hicks, Enoch Wood Perry, William Stark, Theodore Tilton, and Lemuel Wilmarth; patrons Wendell Phillips, J. Hopper, William Walker Scranton, and Francis G. Shaw; writers James Russell Lowell, Charles Frederick Briggs (see also Series 2.2), George W. Curtis, and the actress Charlotte Cushman. An unusually lengthy letter from Page to a young artist "W" (possibly William Stark) about painting is dated 1860. Sophia Page's correspondents include Thomas K. Beecher, Mary Olmsted and Bertha Olmsted.
    See Index for List of Selected Correspondents from Series 2.1.
    Index: List of Selected Correspondents from Series 2.1.
    The following is a selective list of correspondence of William and Sophia Page in Series 2.1: General Correspondence.
    Spellings and abbreviations of names below reflect the actual signatures of letters. Names preceded by question marks indicate partially-legible signatures. Letters with unsigned and illegible signatures which could not be indexed are common in the correspondence, so this index should not be considered comprehensive.
    Adam, Sarah W.: 1877-1878
    Allan, W.G.: 1848
    Allen, Elizabeth Akers: 1863-1864, 1880, 1885-1888, 1892, undated
    Alsop, ?H.J.W.: 1871
    Ammon, W.E.: 1887-1888
    Appleton, Nathan: 1874
    Arcadian Club: 1874
    Armstrong, William: 1889
    Austin Baldwin and Co.: 1863
    Avery, Charles: 1870
    Avery, Sam P.: undated
    Badeau, Adam: 1866
    Baker, H.: undated
    Baker, W.J.: 1874
    Balducci, Y.: 1855
    Bard, M.I.: undated
    Barney, C. H.: 1863
    Barney, Hiram: undated
    Bartholemew, E.: 1855-1856
    Bartlett, C.E.: undated
    Barton, Sam: 1870, 1879
    Bates, L.: undated
    Beardsley, Annie: 1885
    Beatty, John W.: 1900, 1902
    Becker, Dr.: undated
    Beckwith, James Carroll: 1899
    Beecher, Thomas K.: 1850, 1853-1854, undated
    Bellinger, Louis: 1887
    Benedict, Robert D.: 1856, 1876, 1886
    Benedict, Taft, and Benedict: 1880
    Benet, W.V.: 1861
    ?Bennett, J.R.: undated
    Berdam, D.W.: 1861
    Betty, Edward: 1875
    Biglow, L.G.: 1883
    Bigmore, Edward: 1880
    Birney, E.P.: 1865
    Blomeger, Georgina: undated
    Boies, H.M.: 1875-1876
    Bossange, H.: 1855
    Bradford, J.F.: 1870
    Brady, J.R.: 1873
    Brehart, Mary: 1888, undated
    Briggs, Charles Frederick: 1852, 1861, undated (see also series 2.2)
    Briggs, Charlotte "Sharly": 1877, 1882-1883, 1886-1894, 1896, 1899, undated
    Brower, Edith: 1878
    Brown, Henry J.: 1884
    Brown, H.K.: 1871
    Brownell, W.C.: 1889
    Bullard, Laura Curtis: 1875, 1880, undated
    Burt, John: 1860
    Carlin, R.: 1863
    Carpenter, Edward J.: 1873
    Carter, C.M. 1882
    Carter, R.: 1864, 1866, 1872, 1874-1876
    Carter, Susan N.: 1864, 1879, 187?, 1880, 1882, 1884, 1886-1889, 188?, 1891-1892, undated
    Catlin, Henry: 1882
    Centennial Commision: 1876
    Chase, Thomas: undated
    Chase, William M.: 1902
    Cheney, E.D.: 1886
    Cheney, T.A.P.: 1869
    Child, Lydia Marie: 1848, undated
    Chilton, James R.: 1848
    Chilton, R.I.: 1849
    Chilton, W.W.: undated
    Choate, Joseph: 1873
    Clagstone, H. Glassford: 1884
    Clark, Mrs. C.S.: 1871
    Clason, Mrs. A.S.: 1868, undated
    Clemens, Clara: 1886
    Cleveland, Esther Greeley: undated
    Clover, Lewis: 1870, 1880
    Codling, Geroge: 1862
    Conant, B.B. (Harper and Brothers): 1883
    Conant, L.B.: 1877
    Congers, N.S.: 1863
    Cook, Albert S.: 1873
    Corbin, Francis: 1852
    Cornwallis, H.J.: undated
    Cowley, Mrs. Julius D.: undated
    Crawford, L.W.: undated
    Crawford, Thomas: 1853, undated
    Crocker, U.H.: 1875-1876
    Curtis, George W.: 1857, 1870, 1880, 1887
    Cushman, Charlotte (Charles): 1853, 1858, 1874, undated
    Dana, Charles A.: 1854, 1881
    Day, Livy: undated
    ?Decamps, J.: 1880
    Dewy, Julius: 1882
    Dexter, Franklin B.: 1871
    Didama, H.D.: 1867
    Dietz, Linda: undated
    Dixon, O.H.: 1875
    Douglas, Eliza: 1863
    Druker, L.E.: undated
    Dunnel, John H.: 1861, 1863
    Durfee, Rose: 1877, 1879
    Easton, Harriet: undated
    Eliot, Charles W.: 1876
    Elliman, Charles B.: 1870
    ?Evans, Joseph or George: 1874
    Evans, W.W.: 1877
    Fagan, John F.: 1888
    Farrell, M.: 1869
    Fenton, R.: undated
    Fields, Annie: 1860, undated
    French, W.M.R.: 1877
    G.P. Putnam Sons: 1877
    Gale, L.D.: 1848
    Gay, S.H.: undated
    Gibbons, S.J.: 1878
    Gifford, S.R.: 1871, 1873
    Gilder, R.W.: undated
    Godkin, E.L.: 1871-1872
    Godwin, Parke: 1880, undated
    Goodyear, William Henry: 1882-1883
    Gray, David: 1862
    Green, H.H.: 1865
    Guy, S.J.: 1874, 1885, 1887
    Hale, Mrs. E.E.: 1872
    Hall, Anna Maria: 1853, undated
    Hall, E.W.: 1868, undated
    Hammersley, J.W.: undated
    Hannah, George: 1870
    Harper Brothers: 1879
    Harris, Addie A.: 1863
    Hart, Burnham: 1885
    Hart, John S.: 1873
    Hart, Levi Wells: undated
    Hastings, Alice: undated
    Hawkins and Cothren: 1871
    Hazard, W.A.: 1879
    Henderson, Ettie: 1891
    Henry Holt and Co.: 1879
    Hibbard, James N.: 1880
    Hicks, Thomas: 1863, 1868
    Hills, Mrs. Amelia: 1869
    Hinckley, Polly Page: 1873
    Holcombe, Emily: 1886
    Hooker, J.C. (of Packenham and Hooker): 1854-1858, 1860, undated
    Hooper: 1854
    Hopkins, Geraldine: 1863
    Hopper, J.: 1861-1862, undated
    Hoppin, Rosalie: 1858
    Hoppin, William J.: 1857
    Hudson, John: 1883
    Humphreys, Mary Cray: undated
    Hunt, Richard M.: 1868
    Huntington, D: 1878
    Huntington, Frank: 1888-1889
    Hussey, George B.: 1875
    ?Ickelheimer, I.: 1872, 1875
    Ingersoll, W.H.: 1876
    Jay, William: 1888
    Jeremiah, Ann; 1880
    Johnson, B.: 1863
    Johnson, E.H.: 1876-1877
    Johnson, E.N.: 1874
    Johnson, Josephine M.: 1873
    Johnson, Kate: 1886
    Johnston, J.B.: 1869, 1876-1877
    Johnston, Mrs.: 1868
    Keenan, Thomas Jr.: 1889
    Kennedy, James C.: 1858
    Kidney, John S.: 1872
    Kimball, Richard: 1852, 1854
    King, Augustu G.: undated
    King, Clarence: 1875
    Knortz, Karl: 1877
    Knowell, John: 1881
    Kucsczuski, S.W.: 1861
    Kuzynski, Pauline A.: 1855
    Laing, Charles G.: 1885
    Laurie, Alexander: 1870
    Law, S.D.: 1848
    Lester, Mrs. L.: 1877
    Leupp, Charles: 1852
    Lewis, Eliela P.: 1865
    Lewis, Juan: 1873
    Lines, Mary: undated
    Linton, W.J.: 1872-1874, 1876-1886, 1891, undated
    Livingston, John Henry: 1878
    Loring, E.G.: 1857
    Lossing, Bevson J.: 1877
    Low, William H.: 1904-1905
    Lowell, Effie: 1877
    Lowell, James Russell: 1843, 1848, 1874, 1878, 1885-1887, 1889, undated
    Lowell, Josephine S.: 1885, 1887, undated
    Ludlow, E.H.: 1884
    Lyman, Arthur T.: 1876
    M. Knoedler and Co.: 1901
    MacBeth, W.: 1902-1903
    Mackay, W.B.: 1848
    MacPherson, William H.: 1874
    Mansfield, John W.: 1883
    Manton, Walter: 1857